Finding Aid for Lola M. Jones videotapes, 1983-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lola M. Jones videotapes 1983-1995
Jones, Lola M.
96 videotapes (in 8 boxes) U-matic and VHS
9618 Aa 2
Producer of local Ann Arbor, Michigan, cable television programs highlighting achievements of African Americans in the Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti area. Videocassette copies of television program, "Another Ann Arbor" that featured interviews with local area and national African American public figures.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Lola Jones (donor no. 7780 )
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lola Jones was born in Boston, Ma. of Jamaican parents. She graduated from Wayne State University, then moved to Flint, MI where she became active in the community. She came to Ann Arbor in 1964, earning a masters degree in social work from the University of Michigan. During this same period, she became active in the struggle for an open housing ordinance. She then joined the counseling staff of Washtenaw Community College, where she established the Adult Resource Center for non traditional students, and served as its first director. Beginning in the early 1980s, Lola Jones has produced " Another Ann Arbor," a local television program which highlights the achievements of African Americans in the Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti area. The goal of the program was to document and record the contributions of African Americans to the community. In 1991 she produced a documentary on the history of black women in Ann Arbor entitled " A Woman's Town." A follow-up documentary, " A Change was in the Air", produced in 1994, documented the civil rights struggle in Ann Arbor in the 1960's. A third documentary, " Take It to the Top" was a motivational piece directed towards junior high school students. It highlighted the careers of young African Americans who grew up in Ann Arbor, attended local schools and churches, and were then carrying out successful careers in Ann Arbor.
The Lola Jones collection consists of videotapes (mainly U-matic with some VHS copies) of her cable television program Another Ann Arbor, and of the documentaries that she produced. Another Ann Arbor, produced by Lola Jones, was an interview/discussion program hosted by Carole Gibson and featuring as guests locally and nationally prominent African American men and women.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Jones, Lola M.; African Americans--Civil rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Civil rights--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--History.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--History.; Detroit Urban League.; Underground Railroad--Michigan.
Contributors:
Archer, Dennis.; Edwards, Esther.; Fletcher, Robert W.; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; Johnson, Henry.; Parks, Rosa, 1913-2005.; Wheeler, Albert Harold, 1915-1994.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Documentaries, interviews, and miscellaneous
  (u-matic copy unless otherwise indicated)
  - "Another Ann Arbor" promo 1993, vhs tape (Box 1)
    (tape no. unnumbered)
  - "A Woman's Town" (Memories of Ann Arbor to 1950) 1991 (Box 1)
    (tape no. 1)
  - "Take it To The Top" (Successful young adults who grew up in Ann Arbor) 1992, vhs tape (Box 1)
    (tape no. 2)
  - Interview with Rosa Parks December 1993 (Box 1)
    (tape no. 3)
  - "A Change Was In The Air" (Ann Arbor during the Civil Rights era) 1994, u-matic and vhs copies (Box 1)
    (tape no. 4)
  - University of Michigan Mentorship program, vhs tape (Box 1)
    (tape no. 5)
  - Interview with Dr. Albert Wheeler (Box 1)
    (tape no. 6)
  - "A Tribute of Dr. and Mrs. Albert Wheeler" December 1993, vhs tape (Box 1)
    (tape no. 6-a)
  - "Bethel A.M.E. Church Anniversary Pageant" 1993, vhs tape) (Box 1)
    (tape no. 7)
  - Jessie Jackson at Hill Auditorium 1988 (Box 1)
    (tape no. 8)
  - Jessie Jackson interview at Ypsilanti High School. (Box 1)
    (tape no. 8-a)
- Another Ann Arbor (local cable television program)
  - Ann Arbor's earliest African American families. Guest: Coleman Jewett, Local Historian 1983 (Box 1)
    (tape no. 9)
  - VHS copies of shows no. 1-18 (Box 1)
    (tape no. 9-a)
  - Scholarly Research findings on The Black Elderly. Guest: Rose Gibson PhD. Asst. Prof. Univ. of Mich. 1983 (Box 1)
    (tape no. 10)
  - Guest: Jon Onye Lockard Ann Arbor artist, Instructor at University of Michigan and at Washtenaw Community College 1983 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 11)
  - Ann Arbor Board of Education. Guest: Eunice Royster-Harper, Member Ann Arbor Board of Education 1986 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 12)
  - The Bird of Paradise Lounge. Guest: Ron Brooks (Ann Arbor Musician, Owner The Bird of Paradise) 1987 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 13)
  - Food Pantry, Second Baptist Church. Guests: Vera Greer and Johnnie May Balis 1987 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 14)
  - Status of African Americans in Ann Arbor. Guest: Larry Hunter, African American City Councilperson 1987 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 15)
  - Eastern Mich. Univ. Guest: Dr. John Porter. Pres. E.M.U. 1987 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 16)
  - Black Cowboys. Guest: Leroy Ray Jr. 1987 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 17)
  - Ann Arbor Community Center. Guest: Walter Hill, Exec. Dir. Of Center 1989 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 18)
  - Black historical figures in the Ann Arbor / Ypsilanti community. Guest: A.P. Marshall, local historian 1989 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 18-a)
  - ASAC Detroit F.B.I. Guest: Paul Phillip 1989 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 19)
  - Ypsilanti City Commissioner. Guest: Eula Tate 1989 (Box 2)
    (tape no. 20)
  - Experiences in the office. Guest: Dennis Archer, Mich. Supreme Court Justice 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 21)
  - Gifted African American Students in chemistry. Guest: Dr. B.J. Evans, Prof. of Chemistry, University of Michigan 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 22)
  - West Indian Writers. Guest: Brenda Flannigan, Author, Instructor U.M. and Eastern Mich. 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 23)
  - P.O.W. Vietnam. Guest: Robert Fletcher 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 24)
  - Adoption of Black children. Guests: Dr. Terri Johnson and Sylvia Hood 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 25)
  - First Black Judge in Washtenaw County. Guest: Probate Judge Nancy Francis 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 26)
  - No guest. 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 27)
  - First Black Fire Fighter in Washtenaw County. Guest: Floyd Walls 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 28)
  - Physically Challenged Population. Guest: Tommie Washington, Assistant Dir Challenge Inc. 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 29)
  - The Museum. Guest: Dr. Charles Wright. April 1990 (Box 3)
    (tape no. 30)
  - Programs for African American students. Guests: Joseph Dulin, Roberto Clemente Development Center, William Ratcliff, African American Academy 1991 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 31)
  - State of Blacks in Mich. Guest: Joseph Anderson, Exec. General Motors 1991 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 32)
  - African American Writers. Guest: Dr. Deborah Barney 1991 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 33)
  - Guest: Dr. Earl Lewis, Dir. Center for African American Studies University of Michigan 1991 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 34)
  - NAACP ACTSO Program. Guest: Fred McCuiston and Christina Montegue 1991 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 35)
  - Washtenaw Co. Commissioner. Guest: Christina Montague 1991 (Box 4)
  - Status of Black Americans in Mich. Guest: Carl Breeding, Pres. NAACP State Conference 1991 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 36)
  - Quality assurance at Ford Motor Co. Guest: Dr. Willie Hobbs Moore 1991 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 37)
  - Social Commentary. Guest: Ray Pipkin, Artist, Historian, teacher 1989 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 38)
  - The United Negro College Fund. Guest: John Barfield, Entrepreneur CEO Bartec Companies 1992 (Box 4)
    (tape no. 39)
  - Homeless in Ann Arbor. Guest: Larry Fox, advocate for the Homeless 1992 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 40)
  - Guest: Winifred Northcross, First Black Ann Arbor City Clerk 1992 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 41)
  - Reparations for Black Americans. Guest: Ray Jenkins 1991 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 42)
  - Univ. of Mich. "Women of Color Task Force". Guests: Denise White and Monica Johnson 1992 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 43)
  - First African Amer. Principal, Huron High School. Guest: Dr. Joetta Mial 1992 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 44)
  - On location at the Museum. Guest: Esther Edwards, Dir. Motown Museum 1992 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 45)
  - Black Women in Business. Guests: Sherry Toney, Marcia Jordan, Frances Vaughn, Sarah Davis 1992 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 46)
  - Photographs of West Africa. Guest: John Matlock, Admin. University of Michigan 1992 (Box 5)
    (tape no 47)
  - Book, Protégée and Joyce Hunter, African American Cult and Historical Museum. Guest: Marva Allen, Author 1993 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 48)
  - Life story. Guests: Dr. Cannidy first Black Neurosurgeon) and Dr. William Pickard (Mich. Entrepreneur) 1993 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 49)
  - Flemming's Life Experience. Guest: Thomas Flemming 1993 Teacher of the Year, 1993 (Box 5)
    (tape no. 50)
  - Detroit Urban League. Guest: Charles Anderson, Pres. 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 51)
  - Vitigalo, disease that whitens the skin of a Black person. Guest: Johnnie May Freeman 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 52)
  - Traced family history back to Gore Island, W. Africa 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 53)
  - Diseases Affecting Blacks in Particular. Guest: William Goree 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 54)
  - Experiences on U.M. Football team and advice to youth. Guest: Harlan Hucklebee 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 55)
  - Discussion of Kwanza. Guest: Dr. Maulane Karenga, Originator of Kwanza Celebration 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 56)
  - Guest: Gloria Naylor, Nationally known novelist and Faye Wattleton, Pres. Nat Org. of Women (NOW) 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 57)
  - Iraqi Children, Victims of War. Guest: Christine Oram 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 58)
  - Her Life and Work. Guest: Sony Sanchez, nationally known writer and Poet. (Box 6)
    (tape no. 59)
  - "Children First" Program at the Free Press. Guest: Neal Shine, Publisher Detroit Free Press 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 60)
  - Ann Arbor First Black Superintendent. Guest: Dr. John Simpson, Superintendent A.A. Public schools 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 61)
  - Admission to the University of Michigan. Guest: Ted Spencer, U. M. Dir. of Admissions 1993 (Box 6)
    (tape no. 62)
  - History of African folk tales with demonstration. Guest: LaRon Williams, Storyteller 1993 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 63)
  - Astronaut. Guest: Charles Bolling 1993 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 64)
  - Prostate Cancer. Guests: Dr. David Burks and Dr. T. Meadows 1994 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 65)
  - Black Women's Lives. Guest: Elise Bryant 1994 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 66)
  - History and Demonstration of S. Carolina sweet grass baskets. Guest: Mary Jackson, artist, creator of museum quality baskets 1994 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 67)
  - Reunited with his lost family. Guest: Henry Johnson, former vice pres. University of Michigan 1994 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 68)
  - Night Song, 1st African American romance novel; information on Black towns in the old west 1994 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 69)
  - Minority Students at Univ. of Mich. Guest: Dr. Lester Monts Vice Provost, Univ. of Mich 1994 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 70)
  - Dermatology, history and demonstration. Guest: Dr. Lorna Thomas 1994 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 71)
  - African Art at the Museum. Guest: Barbara Krause, University of Michigan Museum of Art 1995 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 72)
  - Sky lab and other flights. Guest: Former Astronaut, Jack Lousma 1995 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 73)
  - Local Issues. Guests: Ray Mullins, Pres. Ypsilanti N.A.A.C.P. and Dr. Harry Williams, Pres. Ann Arbor N.A.A.C.P. 1995 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 74)
  - Guest: Charles Moody 1988 (Box 7)
    (tape no. 75)
  - National Issues. Guest: Shirley Chisolm, former Congresswoman 1994 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 76)
  - Guest: Marva Collins, educator 1987 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 77)
  - Susan Taylor Essence Magazine. (Box 8)
    (tape no. 78)
  - Author of The Africans, Guest: Dr. Ali Mazrui, Prof. Univ. of Mich. 1987 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 79)
  - Editor Black Enterprise. Guest: Earl Graves, 1987 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 80)
  - Travels. Guests: L. Byrd and G. Barnes 1984 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 81)
  - Travel to Russia. Guest: Jo Owens 1985 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 82)
  - Cajun Cooking. Guest: Joseph Vaughn Jr. 1985 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 83)
  - Telethon for African Water Wells. Guests: Ann Arbor chapter of Links 1985 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 84)
  - Black Women and Work. Guest: Francel Wilson and others 1985 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 85)
  - Blacks in Business. Guests: Jim Bradley and John Barfield 1985 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 86)
  - Stevie Wonder day in Saginaw. Guest: Stevie Wonder 1986 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 87)
  - Analysis of Blacks in society. Guest: Alden Morris, sociologist 1985 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 88)
  - The Underground Railroad in Michigan. Guest: Frank Ferguson 1987 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 89)